Good morning.
The subject of today's lecture is options.
And I think maybe I'd better
first define what an option is
before I move to just saying anything about them.
Because some of you may not have encountered them,
because they're not part of everyday life for most people.
Although they are in a sense.
I'll get back to that.
Let me just define terms here.
So, I should turn the light on here.
I don't know where the switch is.
Well, I will just make do.
So, there's two kinds of options.
There's a call and a put.
And the call is a call.
And the put is a call.
OK.
A call option is an
option to buy something at a
specified price.
And the price is called
the exercise price or a strike
price.
Those are synonyms.
And a put option is the
right to sell something at the, I
don't know, specified exercise price.
And it has another term that has to be specified.
And that's the exercise date.
OK.
Options go back thousands of years.
And the price is, it must
have happened before we have any
recorded records.
If you want to buy something, you're thinking of buying
something from someone, but you
don't want to put up the
money today, you go to some
lawyer and say, write up a
contract, I want to buy
an option to buy this thing.
So, for example, if you
are thinking of building a building
that is owned now by a farmer,
but you're not ready to do it,
you may be thinking about it,
you can go to the farmer and
say, I'd like to buy
that corner of that acre there.
I'd like to have the right to buy it.
I'll pay you now for the right.
And you get a lawyer
and you write up a contract.
And that's an option.
You have an option to buy.
And you can do that
at the exercise price until the
exercise date.
Now, in modern terminology, we have two kinds, American and
European.
And it doesn't refer to geography, those two terms.
The terms refer instead to the price.
And the price refers to when you can exercise.
So, the American option is better than the European
option for the buyer, because the American option can be
exercised at any time until the exercise date.
Whereas a European option can be exercised only on the
exercise date.
But you see, the American
option has to be better, or
not worse than.
It's strictly better, but not worse than a European option,
because you have more options.
So, I think we've defined what they are.
Do you understand well enough what they are?
They occur naturally in life.
I remember, Avinash Dixit was writing about options.
And he said, well, when you're dating someone, and you're
not going to marry them, and
you know the person will marry
you, you have an option, which
you can exercise at any time by
agreeing to marry.
Now, one of the theorems
in option theory is, you usually
don't want to exercise a call option early.
And so, Dixit was saying, well,
maybe that's why a lot of
people have trouble getting married.
They don't want to exercise their option early.
What we'll see is that options have option value.
They give you a choice.
And so, there's something there.
When you exercise an option, that means when you actually
buy the thing, or in the case
of a put, sell the thing, then
you're losing the choice.
So, you've given up something.
Of course, you have to also exercise eventually, if things
are going to make sense.
But usually, when we talk about options, we're talking
now about options to buy a
share of stock, or 100 shares
of stock.
And that's the usual example.
But they occur all over the place.
Let me mention some other examples of options.
The usual story is the stock option.
You go to your broker, and you
say, I'd like to buy an option
to buy 100 shares of Microsoft.
I want to buy Microsoft.
I want to buy an option to buy Microsoft.
Which happens to be cheaper, by the way, usually.
Usually, it costs more money
to actually buy the thing than
to buy the right to
buy the thing at another price.
We'll get back to that.
But in a sense, let's think about this.
Stocks themselves are options, in a sense, with a zero
exercise price.
Maybe I'll have to get back to that.
I can explain that.
But what I mean is, let me
get back and explain that in a
minute.
But let me go ahead to other examples.
Mortgages, an ordinary home mortgage has an option
characteristic to it, in the sense
that if the price of your
home drops a lot, you can
just walk away from the mortgage
and say, I'm going to buy this.
And say, I'm out of here.
It's like not exercising an option.
It's analogous.
Or I can choose to prepay a mortgage early.
And that's like exercising an option.
So, option pricing gets into all sorts of things.
Okay.
So, I thought I should say
something about the purposes of options.
I'm not sure if I'm saying it correctly.
But I'm going to give you
a couple of examples of options
before I move on to
try to discuss what their properties
and pricing are, which is
the main subject of this lecture.
Two different justifications for options.
Why do we have options?
Some people cynically think that
options are just gambling vehicles.
It's another way to gamble.
You can go to the casino, you
can play poker, or you can buy options.
Well, I think for some
people, that's just what it is.
They're volatile, risky investments that can
make you a lot of money.
But I think they have a basic purpose.
And so, or purposes.
First of all, theoretical.
If we're trying to design the
ideal financial system, what would we do?
And I think back, some people thought
of ideal economic systems without reference to finance.
Like Karl Marx, I come back to him, the great
communist, thought that we would have an ideal communist state.
And there'd be no financial markets.
When they actually tried it,
and they tried to do it,
I think they gradually realized
that not having any financial markets
makes our entrepreneurship, our management
of enterprises kind of blind.
We can't see where we're going, because there's no prices.
We don't know what anything is worth.
There was an old joke that the
communist countries survived only because they had money.
And that's not true.
The communist countries survived only because they
had prices from capitalist countries to rely on.
Otherwise, they don't know anything about values or profits.
So, we need prices.
And I just traced the,
many people have written about this.
But I mentioned in 1964, Kenneth
Arrow, who is an economic theorist,
wrote a classic paper in which he argued that,
unless we have prices for all states of nature,
there is a sense in
which the economic system is inefficient.
You really need the price of
everything, including the price of some possibility.
And in a sense, that's what options are giving you.
The existence of options.
The existence of options are giving you.
So, Steven Ross, who used to teach
here at Yale, a friend of mine,
lives here in New Haven.
In 1976, in the Quarterly Journal of Economics,
wrote a classic paper about options,
showing that, in a sense, they complete the state space.
They create prices for
everything that affects decision making.
So, I'm not going to get
into the technicalities of the paper,
but I wanted to start
with a theoretical justification for options,
so that you'll see why we're doing it.
I don't want this to come across as a
lecture, how you can gamble in the options market.
This is about making things work right for the economy.
Making things work right for the economic system.
Improving human welfare.
But it seems, a lot of people don't get that.
That's why Karl Marx was so successful.
It seems too abstract.
What does this options market do for us?
But let me just go back
to the example I started out with.
You're a construction firm, and
you're thinking of building something.
A new supermarket, right?
Where people can buy their food.
And you note that there's a
pair of expressways crossing somewhere.
And you think, that's the perfect
place to build a mega supermarket.
Because everyone can get there by car.
And there's a lot of land.
I can build a big parking lot.
Perfect.
But before you think further, you go
to buy an option on the land, right?
So, you knock on the door at the
farmhouse, and there's a farmer with all these acres.
And you say, I'm thinking
of building a mega supermarket here.
I'd like to buy an option on your farm.
You learn something at that moment.
You might learn that the farmer
says, I've already sold an option.
So, I can't do it.
You can try to talk to the person I sold
it to, and see if you can buy it from him.
Or the farmer might say, I've had three other offers, and
I'm raising my price to some millions of millions of dollars.
Then you have a second thoughts about doing it.
You see what I'm saying?
That the price discovery is in there.
It's making things happen differently.
You're learning something.
The farmer is learning something.
You are learning something from the options market.
And ultimately, it decides where that supermarket will go.
So, that's the theoretical purpose of options.
But I wanted to talk also
about a behavioral purpose of options.
It gets a little fuzzier about the
actual benefits of options from this standpoint.
The behavioral theory of options says that, well, it's very,
very many different aspects of human behavior tie into options.
But,
I would say it has something
to do with attention anomalies and salience.
Psychologists talk about this, that people make mistakes
very commonly in what they pay attention to,
what strikes their fancy or their imagination.
Salience is something psychologists also talk about.
That certain kinds of events,
maybe it's similar to salience.
But salience events are events that tend
to attract attention, tend to be remembered.
Now, when you think of options, a lot
of options are what are called incentive options.
And when you get your
first job, you may discover this.
They'll give you options to buy
shares in the company you work for.
Why do they do that?
I think it's because of certain human behavioral traits
that I mentioned here, your attention and your salience.
But it's not necessarily very expensive for a company
to give you options to buy shares in the company.
But it gives you, puts you in a situation where
you start to pay attention to the value of the company.
It becomes salient for you.
And you start hoping that the price of the company will go
up, because you have options to buy it at a strike price.
You hope that the company's price per share goes above
your strike price, because then your options are worth something.
They're in the money.
So, it may change your motivation and your morale
at work, or sense of identity with the company.
All these sorts of things figure in.
And so, that's why we have incentive options.
They can also give you peace of mind.
And insurance is actually related to options in the sense that when you
buy insurance on your house, it's like buying a put option on your house.
Although it may be not directly
connected to the home's value, right?
When you buy an insurance policy on your house and
the house burns down, you collect on the insurance policy.
Well, the price of your house fell to zero.
If you had bought a put option on
the house, it would do the same thing, right?
You would have an option to sell it
at a high price, something that's now worthless.
So, insurance is like options.
And insurance gives you peace of mind.
And so, people think in certain repetitive patterns.
And one of them is that I
would like to not worry about something.
So, I can get peace of mind by not.
But I have a put option on
something that I might otherwise worry about.
Maybe that's enough of an introduction.
But I've given you both theoretical
reasons for options and behavioral reasons.
I think of them as basically inevitable.
You may have people advising you
not to bother with options markets.
And that might be right for you in a sense.
But I think that they're
always going to be with us.
And so, it's something that we have to understand.
So, let me, I have
a newspaper clipping that I took.
I cut it out.
I've been teaching this course for over 20 years.
So, sometimes I don't update my newspaper clippings.
I have a newspaper clipping from the
options page that I made in 2002.
So, that's nine years ago.
But I can't update it anymore.
Because newspapers don't print option prices anymore.
So, I could go on some electronic
trade account and get an updated option page.
But why don't we just
stick with the Wall Street Journal.
So, this is a clipping from the Wall Street Journal.
April 2002.
When they used to have an options page.
Okay.
And I just picked America Online.
Just as, I don't know why, it's an interesting company.
Do you remember America Online?
Web presence.
It used to be bigger than it is now.
And actually, in 2000, America
Online merged with Time Warner.
Okay.
And so, we actually have two different rows corresponding.
Up there, what, forget ACE Limited.
The second row says AOL.TW.
That's America Online, Time Warner, the merged company.
And then, below that, they have America Online itself.
These were options that were issued before the merger.
And they apparently are being exercised.
In terms of the same AOL, Time Warner stock.
AOL, by the way, was spun
off by Time Warner last year.
So, they had a divorce.
They were married in 2000.
They were divorced in 2010.
So, you can get back to AOL options now.
So, anyway, it shows the
price of the share at $21.85.
So, you can take any of these rows.
And it shows you, for various
strike prices, what the options prices are.
So, let's go to the top row.
A strike price of 20, expiring in May of 2020.
Okay.
So, the price of the share of 2002,
which is like one month into the future.
Remember, it's April 2002 right now.
The volume is the number
of options that were traded yesterday.
And the $2.55 up there is
the price of a call option.
The last price, the last option to be traded yesterday.
This is the morning paper.
It's reporting on yesterday morning's prices.
And then, there's put options traded.
A lot more puts were traded on that day.
There were 2,000 put options traded
on that day in April 2002.
And the last price of the put option was $0.85.
So, you see what the – so, for $0.85, you could buy
the right to sell a share of AOL Time Warner at $22.50.
Okay.
And similarly, you could buy the right
to buy it at $20 for $2.55.
So, these are different strike
prices and different exercise dates.
Here's an – this one is
– which one we can pick?
This one, I can reach it.
Is to buy at – well,
if it's a call, $25 strike price.
Cost you 45 cents to buy that.
But if you want to buy
a put, it costs you $3.50.
If you want to buy
a put, it costs you $3.60.
And we want to try to understand these prices.
Okay.
That's the purpose here.
So, let me say one thing
more before I get into that.
This is presented for the potential buyer.
Okay.
These are options prices.
And the seller of the option.
They are called the writer of the option.
I gave you an example before when I talked
about the farmer and you thinking of building a supermarket.
So, you are the buyer of the option
and the farmer is the writer of the option.
The farmer is writing the option to you.
You could also consider buying an option from
someone else who is not even the farmer, right?
It could be some speculator.
You don't have to go to the farmer.
You could go to somebody else and say, I'd
like to buy an option on that farm over there.
And someone says, sure, I'll
sell you an option on it.
And then I'm good for it.
That means I have to go and
buy it at whatever price from the farmer.
Maybe that's not such a good idea.
He might sense my urgency to buy it.
But if it's a stock, someone can write
an option who doesn't even own the stock.
And so, that's called a naked seller of an option.
Okay.
Neither the buyer nor the seller
ever have to trade in the stock.
This is a market by itself.
You know, you could buy an option and then you
could sell it before as an option without ever exercising it.
And so, the writer could write an option and then buy an option
to cancel it out later and then essentially get out of that contract.
So, the option becomes a market of its own.
Where prices are different.
And the prices of options start
to look like an independent market.
And this is called a derivatives market.
Because there's an underlying stock price, but
this is a derivative of the stock price.
They were first traded, the first options
exchange was the Chicago Board Options Exchange.
Which came in in 1973.
Before that, options were traded.
But they were traded through brokers.
And they didn't have the same presence.
You know, you didn't see
all these options prices in newspapers.
It's when they opened the market for options
that the options trading became a big thing.
So, options markets are relatively new.
I mean, if you consider 73 new.
You weren't born then.
But it's not really that long ago.
Since then, there are many more options exchanges.
But CBOE is the first one.
They're now all over the world.
We also have options on futures.
And so, futures exchanges now routinely
trade options on their futures contracts.
So, that's a derivative on a derivative.
But it's done.
Okay.
So, let me draw a simple picture of option pricing.
So, this is the stock price.
And this is the option price.
Okay.
And I'm going to mark here the exercise price.
Then, let's look at the exercise date.
The last day.
Okay, the option is about to expire.
And this is your last chance to buy the stock.
Then it doesn't matter on that
day whether it's an American or European.
It doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter whether it's
an American or European option.
They're both the same on the last day.
What is the price of the option
as a function of the stock price?
Well, if the stock price is less
than the exercise price, the option is worthless.
Right?
It will not be exercised.
You won't exercise an option to buy it for
more than you could just buy it on the market.
Right?
You have to say call.
Did I not say call?
Yes.
I'm going to put it up here.
We're talking about call options.
Thank you.
But if it's above the exercise price, this is a
45-degree angle that's in line with the slope of 1.
The option price rises with the stock price.
In fact, it just equals the
stock price minus the exercise price.
Right?
So, this region, we say, is out of the money.
The option is out of the money when its price
is for a call, is less than the exercise price.
Here, it's in the money.
I'll put it up here, in the money.
And then, on the exercise date, it will
always equal the stock price minus the exercise price.
So, it's very simple.
Now, one confusion that's often made.
I gave the example of building a
shopping center or a supermarket on a farm.
Now, someone might think that you buy an option on it, so
that you can think about it and make up your mind later.
Well, in a sense, you could do that.
But the thing is, you will exercise the option, whether or not
you build the shopping mall or the supermarket, if it's in the money.
Right?
Suppose the farmer, suppose you've changed your mind
and I don't want to build a supermarket.
But I'm sitting on a farm.
But I'm sitting on an option that I bought to buy his
land for a price, which is less than the market price for it.
Of course, I'll buy it.
So, you're going to buy it, whether
you build the shopping center or not.
You always exercise the option, if it's
in the money on the last day.
That's an assumption.
I mean, you could not, I suppose, if you like
the farmer and you want to be a nice guy.
I don't know.
But usually, it's all about, what
it is, is a nonlinear relation.
So, you can't have a nonlinear relation
between the stock price and the derivative.
So, the derivative is a broken
straight line function of the stock price.
Whereas, all the portfolios we construct are linear.
They're straight lines.
They don't have a break in them.
So, it's creating, the option creates
a break in the stock, in the.
And this is why Ross emphasized
that options price something very different.
No portfolio shows you this broken straight line relation.
Now, I wanted to then talk about a put.
What is a put?
Let me erase where it says,
in and out of the money.
But I'll show it.
I'll do this with a dashed line,
so that you'll see which one is.
I'm leaving the call line up.
With a put, a put is out of the money.
Up here, if, I can't really show it too well.
But, if the stock price is above
the exercise price, because you're selling now.
And it's in the money, if the
stock price is less than the exercise price.
I didn't draw that very well.
But that's supposed to be a 45 degree line.
That's 45 degree angle.
Has a slope of minus one.
Right?
So,
I'll show you how to
do that on the exercise date.
Now, it's interesting that there's a pretty
simple pattern here between puts and calls.
What if I buy one
call and I short one put?
Alright?
Or write a put.
Same thing as writing a put and
shorting a put are the same thing.
Alright?
What does that portfolio look like?
Well, if I put that portfolio together.
If I, if I'm, okay, I want to
have a call plus one call minus one put.
Alright?
Well, my portfolio relation to the stock
price is going to look like that.
Right?
It's just going to be a straight line.
So, my portfolio is equal.
So, the value of my portfolio is equal
to the stock price minus the exercise price.
Simple as that.
And my portfolio can be negative now.
Because I've got, I've shorted something.
I can have a negative portfolio value.
So, that's very simple.
You can see that.
This leads us to the put-call parity equation.
Well, if a put minus a call is the
same thing as the stock minus the exercise price,
then the prices should add up, too.
Right?
So, put-call parity.
There's different ways of writing this.
But it says that the stock price
is the same as the exercise price.
Right?
So, the stock price is
the same as the exercise price.
So, the stock price equals, let me see.
The stock price equals the call price minus
put price plus exercise price on the last day,
on the exercise day.
Right?
It's simple.
This is put-call parity.
This is exercise.
This is put-call parity on the exercise day.
Now, let's think about some day before the exercise date.
Well, you know this is going
to happen on the exercise day.
So, any day before the exercise date, the same thing should
hold, except that we've got to make this the present value.
So, we've got to make this
the discounted value of the exercise price.
And also, we have to add in, in case there
is any dividends paid between now and the exercise date,
plus the present discounted value of dividends
paid between now and the exercise date.
Because the stock gets that, and the option holders don't.
Okay?
So, that's called the put-call parity relation.
And now, I can cross out exercise date.
This should hold on all dates.
Because if it didn't hold, there
would be an arbitrage, a profit opportunity.
So, it should hold on this
page, except for minor failures to hold.
It should hold approximately on this page.
So, let me give you one example.
See if it holds.
Let's consider the following.
Let's consider the one that I can reach.
Let's see.
The strike price.
Okay, what is the, this is the stock price.
So, what do I have?
The biggest thing here is the strike price, exercise price.
So, we want to do $25.
We'll do this line.
$25 plus 45 cents minus $3.60.
And I'm assuming there's no dividend paid.
I mean, there's no dividend paid between now and May.
It comes out very close to $21.85.
I can't do the arithmetic in my head.
It may not hold exactly, because these prices may
not all have been quoted at exactly the same time.
And there's some transaction costs that limit this.
Do you see that now?
So, because of put-call parity relation, the Wall Street Journal
didn't even need to bother to put the put prices in.
Because you can get one from the other.
But they do put them in,
just because people like to see them.
While some people might be trying
to profit from the put-call parity arbitrage.
But for our purposes, we
only have to do call pricing.
Once we've got call pricing, we've got put prices.
I just use the put-call parity
relation, and I get put prices.
So, now let's think about how you would price puts.
The price of a put is, let's just, we
know what it is on the exercise date, right?
I'm going to forget the dashed lines.
There's no dashed lines here anymore.
We're just talking about call prices.
All right.
So, what is the price of a put?
So, this shows the price of
a put on the last day.
Of a call, of a call on the last day.
Now, what about an earlier day?
Well, the price of a
call can never be negative, right?
So, the call price has to be above this line.
It can never be worth less than
the stock price minus the exercise price.
Even before the date.
And also, it can't be worth
more than the stock price itself.
I'll draw a 45 degree line from the origin.
So, it's kind of obvious that the,
that's supposed to be parallel to that.
It's obvious that the call price has
to be above this broken straight line.
But not too far above it.
It's above this broken straight line representing the price as
a function of the stock price on the last day.
And the closer you get to the last day,
the closer the options price will get to that curve.
So, on some day before the exercise date, the option
price, the call option price will probably look something like that.
Right?
It's above the broken straight line because of option value.
So, think of it this way.
Suppose an option is out of the money today.
Well, we can see out of the money options.
This is an out of, for a
call, this is out of the money.
Right?
Because the stock price is $21.85, but I've
got an option to buy it for $25.
That's going to be worthless unless the
option price goes up before it expires.
So, it's only worth something because there's a chance
that it will be worth something on the exercise date.
And what are people paying for that chance?
45 cents.
Not much.
Why are they paying so little?
Well, you could say intuitively,
it's because it's pretty far.
$21.85 is pretty far from $25.
And this option only has a month to go.
What's the chances that the
price will go up that much?
Well, there is a chance.
But it's not that big.
So, I'm only willing to pay 45
cents to buy an option like that.
So, we're somewhere like here on
that row that I've showed you.
But the reason you don't want to exercise an
option early is because if you exercise it early,
your value drops down to the broken straight line.
Right?
It's always worth more than the broken straight line.
And the broken straight line
indicates before the exercise date.
So, if you want to get
your money out, sell the option.
Don't exercise it early.
So, that's why the distinction between European and American options is
not as big or as important as you might think at first.
So, we can just price European options.
And then,
we can infer what put options would be worth.
So, let's now talk about pricing of options.
The main pricing equation that we're going
to use is the Black-Scholes option pricing equation.
But before that,
I wanted to just give you
a simple story of options pricing,
just to give you some idea how it works.
And then I'm going to
not actually derive the Black-Scholes formula,
but I'm going to show it to you.
But the simple,
I'm going to tell you a simple
story just to give you some intuitive feel
about pricing of options.
And to simplify the story,
I'm going to tell a story about a world in
which there's only two possible prices for the underlying stock.
That makes it binomial.
There's only two things that can happen.
And it can either be high or low.
All right.
So, let me get my notation.
I'm going to use S as the stock price.
All right.
So, let me get my notation.
And then I'm going to use,
I'm going to assume that the stock price,
that's today's, that's today.
And this is also a simple
world in that there's only one day.
The option expires tomorrow.
There's only one more price we're going to see.
So, the stock is either
going to go up or down.
So, U is equal to 1 plus
the fraction up, that it goes up.
U stands for up.
And D is down, is 1 plus the fraction down.
So, that means that the stock price either becomes SU,
which means it goes up by a fraction, multiple U,
or it is SD, which means
it goes down by a multiple D.
And that's all we know.
Okay.
Now, we have a call option
called C, the price of the call.
We're going to try to derive what that is.
But we know what, from our broken straight line analysis,
we know what CU is, the
price if the stock goes up.
And we know what CD
is, it's the price if down.
Okay.
So, suppose the option has exercise price E.
All right.
You understand this world's simple story.
Now, what I want to do is consider a portfolio
of both the stock and the option that is riskless.
And I'm going to do this.
I'm going to buy a
number of options equal to H.
H is the hedge ratio, which
is the number of shares sold,
of shares purchased per option sold.
I'm going to sell a call
option to hedge the stock price.
To reduce the risk of the stock price.
Okay.
And so, hedge ratio is
shares sold, shares purchased over options.
Each option is to buy one share.
Okay.
So, what I'm going to do is
write one call and buy H shares.
So, let me erase this and start over again.
Okay.
So, I'm going to buy one call.
I'm on my way to
deriving the options price for you.
And it's a little bit of math, but we'll get.
Okay.
So, I'm going to write
one call and buy H shares.
Okay.
So, I'm going to write one call.
And buy H shares.
Okay.
So, I'm going to write one call.
And I'm going to write one call.
Okay.
If the stock goes up, if we live in an
up, if we discover we're in an up world next period,
my portfolio is worth UHS minus C sub U. Right?
Because the share price goes from S to U.S.
And I've got H shares.
So, I'm going to buy one call.
And I'm going to write one call.
And I've written a call.
So, I have to pay C sub U.
If it's down, then my portfolio
is DHS minus C sub D. Okay.
This is simple enough.
Now, what I want to do is eliminate.
I want to eliminate all risk.
So, that means I want to choose H,
so that these two numbers are the same.
And if I do that, I've got a riskless investment.
All right?
So, set these equal to each other.
And that implies something about H.
We can derive what H is.
I just put these two equal
to each other and solve for H.
And I get H equals UHS.
So, I've got C sub U minus C
sub D all over U minus D S. Okay?
So, I've been able to put together a portfolio
of the stock and the option that has zero risk.
It's going to, if I do this, if I hold this
amount of shares in my portfolio, I've got a riskless portfolio.
So, that means that the riskless
portfolio has to earn the riskless rate.
Right?
It's the same thing as a riskless rate.
So, it has to earn that.
If I can erase this now.
I'm almost there to option pricing.
The option pricing then says that
since I've derived what H is,
the portfolio has to be worth 1.5.
So, I'm going to put in the value of 1 plus the
interest rate times what I put in, which is HS minus C.
And that has to equal the value of the portfolio at the end,
which is either UHS minus C sub U or DHS minus C sub D.
The same thing.
Okay?
So, I've already derived what H is.
And I substitute it into that.
And I solve for C.
So, substitute H in and solve for C.
And we get the call price.
Okay?
And it's kind of a little bit complicated.
But I'll write it.
Call option price has to equal 1.5.
And it has to equal 1 plus R minus D all over U minus D times C sub U over 1
plus R plus U minus 1 minus R all over U minus D times C sub D all over 1 plus R.
And I'll put a box around that.
Because that's our option price formula.
Okay?
Did you follow all that?
This is derived, this option price formula
was derived from a no arbitrage condition.
Arbitrage in finance means riskless profit opportunity.
And the no arbitrage condition says it's never
possible to make more than the riskless rate risklessly.
Alright?
If I could, suppose I had some way.
Suppose the riskless rate is 5%.
And I can make 6% risklessly.
Then I will borrow at the riskless
rate and put it into the 6% opportunity.
And I'll do that till kingdom come.
There's no limit to how much I'll do that.
I'll do it forever.
And so, it can't, it's too much
of a profit opportunity to ever happen.
So, one of the most powerful insights of theoretical
finance is that the no arbitrage condition should hold.
It's like saying there are
no $10 bills on the pavement.
When you walk down the street and you see a $10 bill lying there
on the street, your first thought ought to be, are my eyes deceiving me?
Because somebody else would have picked
it up if it were there.
How can it be there?
I once actually had that experience.
I was walking down the street in New York
and I saw it was actually a $5 bill.
It was just lying there on the street.
And so, I reached down to pick
it up and then suddenly it disappeared.
And it was people on one of the stoops
of one of these New York townhouses playing a game.
They had tied a string to a $5 bill.
And they would leave it on the street.
And watch people reach for
it and they'd snatch it away.
That's the only time in my life I
ever saw a $5 bill on the pavement.
And so, you know, it sounds like a pretty
good assumption that if you see one, it isn't real.
And that's all this is saying.
If the option price didn't follow
this formula, something would be wrong.
And so, it had better follow this formula.
Now, that is the basic core option theory.
Now, the interesting thing about this theory is,
I didn't use the probability of
up and the probability of down.
So, somebody said, wait a minute.
My whole intuition about options is, I buy
an option because it might be in the money.
When I was just describing here, this is 45 cents.
I said, that's not much
because it probably won't exceed $25.
It's so far below it.
So, that's the problem.
So, it seems like the options should really
be fundamentally tied to the probability of success.
But it's not here at all.
There's no probability in it.
You saw me derive it.
Was I tricking you?
Well, I wasn't.
I mean, I tell you, I don't play tricks.
This is absolutely right.
You don't need to know the probability that
it's in the money to price an option.
Because you can price it out of pure no-arbitrage condition.
So, that leads me then to
the famous formula for options pricing,
the Black-Scholes option pricing formula,
which looks completely different from that,
but it's a kindred because
it relies on the same theory.
And there it is.
This was derived
in the late 70s by
Fisher Black, or maybe early 70s,
by Fisher Black, who was at
MIT at the time, I think,
but later went to Goldman Sachs.
And Myron Scholes, who is now
in San Francisco, doing very well.
I see him at our Chicago Mercantile Exchange meeting.
Fisher Black passed away.
So, it doesn't have the probability that
the option is in the money either.
But it looks a little different.
It looks totally different from the
formula that I wrote over there.
The call price is equal to the share price, S,
times N of D1,
where D1 is this equation.
And the call price is
equal to the share price, S,
minus E to the minus R, the interest rate,
times time to maturity, T,
times the exercise price, times N of D2,
where this is D2.
And the N function is
the cumulative normal distribution function.
I'm not going to derive all that,
because it involves what's
called the calculus of variations.
I don't think most of you have learned that.
In ordinary calculus, we have what's called differentials,
dy, dx, etc.
Those are fixed numbers in ordinary calculus.
In the mid-20th century, mathematicians,
notably the Japanese mathematician Ito,
developed a random version of calculus,
where dx and dy are random variables.
That's called the stochastic calculus.
But I'm not going to derive this.
But you can see how
to price an option using black-Scholes.
But black-Scholes is derived, again,
by the no-arbitrage condition,
and it doesn't have the probability.
Oh, the other variable that's significant here is sigma,
which is the standard deviation of
the change in the stock price.
So, once we put that in, someone could say,
well, but probabilities are getting
in through the back door,
because this is really a probability-weighted sum
of the changes in stock prices.
Well, probabilities were not really in here at all,
but maybe there's something like standard deviation
even in this equation, because we had cu and cd,
and that gives you some sense of the variability.
But I'm willing to go on.
I'm going to leave this equation
just for you to look at.
But what it does do is, it shows the stock,
the option price as a nice curve, a linear relationship,
just like the one I drew by hand,
which then, as time to exercise goes down,
as we get close to the exercise date,
that curve eventually coincides
with the broken straight line.
So, now I wanted to tell you about implied volatility.
This equation can be used either of two ways.
The most normal way to
do it, to use this equation,
is to get the price that you
think is the right price for an option,
to decide whether I'm paying too
much or too little for an option.
So, with this formula,
I can plug in all the numbers.
To use this formula,
I have to know what
the stock price is, that's S,
I have to know what the exercise price is,
and I have to know what the time to maturity.
These are all specified by
the stock price and the contract.
I have to know what the interest rate is.
And if I also have
some idea of the standard deviation
of the change in the option of the stock price,
then I can get an option price.
But I can also turn it around,
if I already know what the
option is selling for in the market,
and I can infer what the implied sigma is, right?
Because all the other numbers
in the Black-Scholes formula are clear.
They're in the newspaper or they're in the option contract.
There's this one hard to pin down variable.
What is the variability of the stock price?
And so, what people often use the Black-Scholes formula to,
is to invert it.
And calculate the implied volatility of stock prices.
So, when call option prices are high,
why is that, why are
they high relative to other times?
Well, it must be that people think,
and going back to the old interpretation,
that the probability of exercise is high.
Right? If an out-of-the-money call is valuable,
it must be people think that sigma is high.
So, let's actually solve for how high that is.
I can't actually solve this equation.
I have to do it numerically.
But I can calculate for any call price,
given the stock price, exercise price, time to maturity,
and interest rate, I can calculate what
volatility would imply that stock price.
And so, that's where we are with Black-Scholes.
So, implied volatility,
is the options market's opinion
as to how variable the stock market will be
between now and the exercise date.
So, one thing we can do is compute implied volatility.
And I have that here on this chart here.
What I have here from 1986 to the present,
with the blue line, is the VIX,
V-I-X, which is computed now
by the Chicago Board Options Exchange.
When the CBOE was founded, they
didn't know how to do this.
Black and Scholes invented their equation
in response to the founding of the CBOE.
And now the CBOE publishes the VIX.
And you get on their website,
that's where I got this off their website, cboe.com.
And so, they have computed,
based on the front month option,
the near option, what the market thought the volatility,
what the options market thought the
volatility of the stock market was.
That's the blue line.
And you can see, it had
a lot of changes through time.
That means that options prices were revealing something
about the volatility of the stock market.
Now, the blue line is
from the Chicago Board Options Exchange.
What I did, and I calculated this myself,
is the orange line is the standard deviation
of actual stock prices over the preceding year
of monthly changes annualized.
That's actual volatility.
But it's actual past volatility.
Let's make it clear what this is.
What the VIX is, is
the sigma in the Black-Scholes equation.
But it is, in effect, the
market's expected standard deviation of stock prices.
And to get it more precise, it's the standard deviation
of the S&P 500 stock price index for one month,
multiplied by the square root of 1.
And the S&P 500 stock
price index is the standard deviation
of the S&P 500 stock price index for one month,
multiplied by the square root of 12,
because they want to annualize it.
It's for the next month.
So, it's, why do they multiply
it by the square root of 12?
Well, that's because, remember, the square root rule.
These stock prices are
essentially independent of each other,
month to month.
So, the standard deviation of the sum of 12 months
is going to be a square root of 12
percent per year.
So, that means that the
implied volatility in 1986 was 20%.
And then it shot way up to 60%, unimaginably.
In fact, that might be the record high.
I can't quite tell from here.
Remember, I told you the story
of the 1987 stock market crash?
The stock market fell over 22% in one day.
Well, actually, on the S&P, it was only 20%.
But a lot in one day.
It really spooked the options markets.
So, the call option prices went way up,
thinking that there's some big volatility here.
We don't know which way it'll be next.
Maybe it'll be up, maybe it'll be down.
It pushed the implied volatility
temporarily up to a huge level.
It came right back down.
My actual volatility, now this is,
I calculated this for each date,
as the volatility of the market over the preceding year.
Well, since I put October 1987 in my formula,
I got a jump up in actual volatility.
But not all as big as the options market did.
So, the option market is looking ahead.
And I have no way to look ahead
other than to look at the options market.
So, to get my actual volatility, I was
obliged to look at volatility in the past.
And it went up because
of the 1987 stock market crash.
So, I was able to look at the
volatility in 1987 volatility, but not so much.
So, what this means is
that in 1987, people really panicked.
They thought something is really
going on in the stock market.
They didn't know what it
was, and they were really worried.
And that's why we see this spike in implied volatility.
There's a couple other spikes that I've noted.
The Asian financial crisis occurred in the mid-1990s.
Now, that is something that was primarily Asian.
But it got people anxious over here as well.
It was, you know, Korea, Taiwan, Indonesia, Hong Kong.
These countries had huge turmoil.
But it came over here in the
form of a sudden spike in expected volatility.
People thought things could really happen here.
So, all the option prices got more valuable.
And then there's this spike.
This is the one that you remember.
This is the financial crisis.
This is the financial crisis that
occurred in the last few years.
Notably, it peaks in the fall of 2008,
which was the real crisis when Lehman Brothers collapsed.
And it created a crisis all over the world.
There was a sharp and sudden terrible event.
And you can see that actual volatility shot up
to the highest since 1986 as well at that time.
So, implied volatility, you know, you can't ask easily
from this chart whether it was right or wrong.
People were responding to information.
And the response felt its way into options prices.
What actually, there's no way to find out ex
post whether they were right to be worried about that.
But they were worried about these events.
And it led to big jumps in options prices.
Now, I wanted to show the
same chart going back even further.
But I can't do it with options
prices because I can show volatility earlier.
But I can't show implied volatility before around
1986 because the options markets weren't developed yet.
But I computed an actual.
S&P composite volatility.
Well, in my chart title, I said S&P 500.
The Standard & Poor's 500 Stock
Price Index technically starts in 1957.
But I've got what they call the
Standard & Poor's Composite back to 1871.
And so, these are the actual
moving standard deviations of the price.
And the volatility of stock prices.
All the way back to the beginnings
of the stock market in the U.S.
Well, not the very beginnings, but earliest that
we can get consistent data on a monthly basis.
And you can see, this goes
back further than the other chart.
You can see that the actual
volatility of stock prices has been,
except for one big event,
the recession of the 1930s,
has been remarkably stable.
The volatility in the late 20th century, early 21st century,
is just about exactly the same
as the volatility in the 19th century.
It's interesting how stable these patterns are.
There was this one really anomalous event.
And it just sticks out.
And that is,
the Great Depression.
1929 precedes it.
It's somewhere in here.
But somehow people got really rattled
by the 1929 stock market crash.
And not just in the U.S.
This is U.S. data, but you'll
find this all over the world.
It led to a full decade of
tremendous stock market volatility around the world.
That has never been repeated since.
The recent financial crisis has the
second highest volatility after the Great Depression.
This isn't long ago.
This is well within your memories.
It's just a few years ago.
We had another huge impact on volatility.
And as you saw in the preceding slide,
it had a big impact on implied volatility as well.
So, I think that we had
a near miss of another depression.
It's really scary what happened in this crisis.
Also shown here is the first oil crisis,
which we talked about in 1974,
when oil prices, they had been locked into a pattern
because of the stabilization of oil prices.
So, it was a stabilization
done by the Texas Railroad Commission.
But when that broke, when OPEC first flexed its muscles,
it created a sense of new reality.
And it caused fear.
And it caused a big spike
up in volatility of the stock market.
But not quite as big as the current financial crisis.
So, I think this is an interesting chart to me.
Because it shows that financial markets,
well, a lot of things I learned from this,
and maybe I'll just conclude with some thoughts about this.
But what I learned from this chart is that
somehow financial markets are very stable for a long time.
So, it would seem like it
wouldn't be that much of an extrapolation.
When are you people going to retire?
You've picked a retirement date yet?
Well, let's say a half century from now, okay?
So, that would be 2060.
So, you're going to retire out here.
Your whole life is in here.
What do you think volatility is
going to do over that whole period?
Well, just judging from the
plot, it's probably pretty similar, right?
I mean, that's not much more
history compared to what we've already seen.
Probably just going to keep doing this.
But there's this risk of
something like this happening again.
And we saw a near miss here.
But we didn't have it.
I think this plot encourages me to think that
maybe outliers or fat tails or black swan events
are the big disruptor to economic theory.
Black shoals is not a black swan theory.
It assumes normality of distributions.
And so, it's not always reliable.
So, this leads me to think that
option pricing theory, I've presented a theory.
The black shoals theory is very
elegant and a very useful tool.
Especially useful when things behave normally.
But I think one always has to keep in the back of
one's mind the risk of sudden major changes like we've seen here.
So, let me just give a quick summary.
So, let me just give some final thoughts about options.
I launched this lecture by saying they're very important.
And they affect our lives in many ways.
I've been trying to campaign for
the expansion of our financial markets.
Working with my colleagues
and the Chicago Mercantile Exchange,
we launched options in 2006 on
single-family homes in the United States.
We were hoping that people would buy put
options to protect themselves against home price declines.
But the market never took off.
We have since seen huge human suffering because of the
failure of people to protect themselves against home price declines.
There are things.
Various noises that were made by people in
power that suggested that maybe something could be done.
President Obama proposed something
called Home Price Protection Program.
And it sounded like an option, a put option program.
But actually, it was a
much more subtle program than that.
It was a program to incentivize mortgage originators to
do workouts on mortgages if the mortgages would default.
If home prices were to fall.
And nothing really happened with it.
The President can't get things started either, always.
I've been proposing that mortgages should have
put options on the house attached to them.
When you buy a house, get a
mortgage, you should automatically get a put option.
I've got a new paper on that.
But these are kind of futuristic things at the moment.
But my sense, I'm just saying this at
the end just to try to impress on you
what I think is the real future of mortgage.
What I think is the real importance of options markets.
People don't manage risks well in the present world.
Having options or insurance-like contracts of an expanded
nature will help people manage their risks better.
And it will make for a better world.
Okay, I'll see you on Monday.